<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A relation of the glorious triumphs and order of the ceremonies, obserued in the marriage of the high and mighty Charles, King of Great Brittaine, and the Ladie Henretta [sic] Maria, sister to the most Christian King of France Together vvith the ceremonie obserued in their troth-plighting, performed in the castle of the Louure, in his Maiesties chamber there. As also the Kings declaration containing a prohibition vnto all his subiects to use any traffique or commerce with the kingdome of Spaine. Published in the Parliament of Paris, the 12. of May, 1625. Whereunto the originall French copie is added.</title>
            <title>Ceremonies et solennitez observees en l'eglise de Nostre Dame de Paris, au mariage du roy de la Grand' Bretagne, &amp; de Madame soeur du roy. English and French.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18468</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5029</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107752</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843448</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843448</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8183</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18468)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8183)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1132:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A relation of the glorious triumphs and order of the ceremonies, obserued in the marriage of the high and mighty Charles, King of Great Brittaine, and the Ladie Henretta [sic] Maria, sister to the most Christian King of France Together vvith the ceremonie obserued in their troth-plighting, performed in the castle of the Louure, in his Maiesties chamber there. As also the Kings declaration containing a prohibition vnto all his subiects to use any traffique or commerce with the kingdome of Spaine. Published in the Parliament of Paris, the 12. of May, 1625. Whereunto the originall French copie is added.</title>
                  <title>Ceremonies et solennitez observees en l'eglise de Nostre Dame de Paris, au mariage du roy de la Grand' Bretagne, &amp; de Madame soeur du roy. English and French.</title>
                  <author>France. Sovereign (1610-1643 : Louis XIII). Proclamations, 1625-05-12.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T[homas] S[nodham and others] for Nathaniel Butter, and are to be sold at the signe of the Pyde-Bull, neere S. Austens Gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1625.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of "Ceremonies et solennitez observees en l'eglise de Nostre Dame de Paris, au mariage du roy de la Grand' Bretagne, &amp; de Madame soeur du roy", with the French text following.</note>
                  <note>The "Kings declaration" is that of Louis XIII.</note>
                  <note>Cf. Folger catalogue, which gives signatures: A-C⁴.</note>
                  <note>"Snodham app[arently]. pr[inted]. only quire A"--STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649.</term>
               <term>Henrietta Maria, --  Queen, consort of Charles I, King of England, 1609-1669.</term>
               <term>Commercial law --  France --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8183:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8183:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A RELATION OF THE GLORIOVS TRIVMPHS AND ORDER of the Ceremonies, obſerued in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of the High and Mighty CHARLES, King of <hi>Great Brittaine,</hi> and the Ladie HEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RETTA MARIA, Siſter to the moſt Chriſtian King of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>TOGETHER</hi> WITH THE CEREMONIE obſerued in their <hi>Troth-plighting,</hi> perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the Caſtle of the <hi>Louure,</hi> in his Maieſties Chamber there.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AS ALSO</hi> THE KINGS DECLARATION containing a Prohibition vnto all his Subiects to vſe any Traffique or Commerce with the Kingdome of Spaine. Publiſhed in the Parliament of <hi>Paris,</hi> the 12. of May, 1625.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whereunto the Originall French Copie is added.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Printed by <hi>T. S.</hi> for <hi>Nathaniel Butter,</hi> and are to be ſold at the ſigne of the Pyde-Bull, neere S. <hi>Auſtens</hi> Gate, 1625.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="description">
            <pb facs="tcp:8183:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8183:2"/>
            <head>THE GLORIOVS TRIVMPH AND ORDER OF THE Ceremonies obſerued in the Marriage of the High and Mightie CHARLES King of <hi>Great Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine,</hi> and the Lady HENRETTA MARIA, Siſter to the moſt Chriſtian King of <hi>FRANCE.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>OW at laſt, God being fauourable vnto our Countrey of <hi>France,</hi> hath pleaſed to grant what wee moſt deſired ſo long ſince; and thoſe thicke cloudes which ſeemed to obſcure the luſtre of our Country, and had as it were conſpired to kill the fruite thereof in the very bloſſome, are now ſcattered and blowne ouer, together with the bad influence which threatned vs, God in his ſecret will permitting that two of the moſt mighty and potent King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of Chriſtendome, ſhould be vnited together, by the moſt glorious Marriage that euer was ſeene in the world. Therefore now our Inuincible King <hi>Lewis the Iuſt,</hi> muſt needes promiſe to himſelfe all felicity, glory and happineſſe heaped vpon him by this Vnion.</p>
            <p>What great contentment hath <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Great Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine</hi> profit, to ſee themſelues ſo inſeparably vnited, by a more vndiſſoluable knot then the <hi>Gordian,</hi> and by a friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip better cimmented together, then the Stones of the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilonian walles, founded by <hi>Semiramis?</hi> For neuer ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:8183:3"/> any enemies be found ſtrong enough to ſhake two ſo flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing Kingdomes, which deriue their greatneſſe from heauen, and their limits from the circumference of the Globe: Let all good Frenchmen now then reioyce, at ſuch time as the aduerſaries of our State, trembling with amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and feare, haue their very ſoules afflicted with ſo goodly an alliance: And that I may leaue an eternall me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory thereof vnto all poſterity, I will moſt ſuccinctly here declare, the magnificent triumphes and true manner of this happy marriage.</p>
            <p>ON Thurſday, the 8. day of May, the King came forth into his Chamber, and there appeared like the glorious Sunne, out-ſhining the other Starres, hauing his Queene with him, his ſecond light: the Prince his onely brother, my Lords the Dukes of <hi>Nemours,</hi> and of <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beuf,</hi> the Marſhals of <hi>Vitry</hi> and <hi>Baſſompiere,</hi> with other Lords of his Court, and ſent for the Ladie his Siſter, who came thither accompanyed with the Queene her mother, the Princeſſes of <hi>Conde</hi> and of <hi>County;</hi> the Dutcheſſes of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> of <hi>Cheureuſe,</hi> and <hi>Elbeuf,</hi> with many other great Ladies. Her Gowne was of cloth of gold and ſiluer, all poudered ouer with Flower-deluces of gold, and enriched with many Diamonds, and other precious ſtones, and her traine was borne vp by the yong Ladie of <hi>Burbon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As ſhe entred into the Kings Chamber, with a Maieſtie correſpondent to her birth, my Lords the Earls of <hi>Carlile</hi> &amp; <hi>Holland,</hi> Embaſſadours for the King of <hi>Great Britaine,</hi> came likewiſe alſo in, as richly clad as can poſſibly be expreſſed, giuing vnto the King the Contract of Marriage, which was read alowd by the Lord Chancellour, after the King had agreed vnto the Couenants. This done, the Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadours with-drew themſelues into the Duke of <hi>Cheureuſe</hi> his Chamber, which was ouer the Kings, and hauing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated
<pb facs="tcp:8183:3"/> the Contract vnto him: He forthwith repaired vnto his Maieſtie, accompanied with the afore-ſaid Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors, and many other great Lords, apparelled in a Sute of Blacke, the Paines whereof were all garniſhed with Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, and the very tags of his points were enriched with the like.</p>
            <p>Being come before his Maieſtie, he preſented vnto him his Procuration, and the power which the King of great Brittaine had giuen him, which was inſerted at the end of the ſaid Contract, which the King ſigned, and the Lady, both the Queenes, my Lord the Duke of <hi>Cheureuſe,</hi> and the Lords Ambaſſadors likewiſe. This done my Lord the <hi>Cardinall De la Roche Foucault</hi> made them ſure, after the manner accuſtomed.</p>
            <p>Now as ſuch an vnion as this could not be performed without great pompe, and infinite ioy and contentment: So our <hi>Ladies Church</hi> was choſen for the Ceremonies of the accompliſhment of the Marriage and was hung with rich tapiſtry and cloth of Gould and Siluer Tiſſue.</p>
            <p>Then was there a faire and long Gallery raiſed, begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning at the entry of the Archbiſhops pallace, and reached euen vnto the Quire of the ſaid Church: This gallery was vnder-propped with many pillers, which were couer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the top with Violet-colour Sattin, embrodered with golden Flowre-deluces, and below with faire fine lynnen, trimmed with waxe, through this ſame paſſed along all the Ceremonies of the Marriage as followeth.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the hundred Suiſſers of the Kings Guard, clothed in his Maieſties Lyuery, their Drumbe beating and their Enſigne diſplayed. After them 12. <hi>Haulbois</hi> clothed in the like lyuery, which rauiſhed the hearts of the hearers. Then eight Drumbes couered with the like, which were ſo luſtily beaten vp, that the moſt coward courages were animated with the noyſe thereof.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8183:4"/>
            <p>Ten Trumpets alſo ſounded ſo merrily that it reioyced all the hearers. Then followed <hi>Monſieur de Rhodes,</hi> great Maiſter of the Ceremonies, brauely apparelled, and well accompanied. After him marched my Lords the Knights of the <hi>Order of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> all gliſtering with precious ſtones. Then came ſeauen Heraulds of Armes with their Coats of Red Crimſon Veluet, powdered all ouer with golden Flower-deluces.</p>
            <p>Then followed them my Lords of <hi>Vitry</hi> and <hi>Baſſompiere, Marſhals</hi> of <hi>France:</hi> After them my Lord the Duke of <hi>Elbeuf.</hi> Then my Lord the Duke of <hi>Cheureuſe,</hi> apparelled in a Sute of Blacke-Cloath, cut and lyned with cloath of Gould, with a Cap alſo of cloath of Gould, and vpon his head a Iewell, which dazelled the eyes of the beholders, a Scarfe ſpotted all ouer with Roſes of Diamonds, with a ſhort Cloake all imbroidred with Gold, and powdred with precious ſtones.</p>
            <p>Then followed both my Lords the Ambaſſadors Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary of the King of Great Brittaine, &amp;c. clad in cloth of ſiluer.</p>
            <p>Then came the King of <hi>France,</hi> in a garment all imbroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred with Gold and Siluer, holding the Lady his Siſter in his right hand, who had a crowne vpon her head, and her Gowne powdred all ouer with Flower-deluces of Gold: And <hi>Monſieur</hi> the Kings Brother on the other ſide, who led her in his left hand, being very brauely accoutred.</p>
            <p>The Queene Mother followed next.</p>
            <p>The Queene her ſelfe, in a gowne all imbroidred with Gould, Siluer, and precious ſtones. The Princeſſes of <hi>Conde</hi> and of <hi>County</hi> bearing vp the long Traine of the ſame. The young Lady of <hi>Montpenſier.</hi> The Counteſſe of <hi>Seiſons.</hi> Madame <hi>De Guiſe.</hi> Madame <hi>De Chereuſe.</hi> Madame <hi>De Elbeuf,</hi> with many Lords and Ladies, of whom I cannot now make rehearſall the number of them was ſo great.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8183:4"/>
            <p>All this Royall and generous troupe ſtayed at the entry of the great Portall of the ſaid Church, before which was a place appointed to celebrate the Marriage in, and whereon was raiſed a Canopie of ineſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vallew, vnder which the King and Monſieur his Brother left the Ladye their Siſter, and conſigned her into the hands of my Lord the Duke of <hi>Chevreuſe,</hi> and then my Lord Cardinall <hi>de la Roche Foucault</hi> eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powſed the Ladye with the ordinarie ceremonies of the Church.</p>
            <p>From thence all the Orders aboue ſaid marched in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Quyer through a long Gallerie which was ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out by a line, in the middeſt of the body of the Church all couered with Tapiſterie, the richeſt that might be.</p>
            <p>In the middeſt of the ſaid Quyer were all ready pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced on the one ſide vpon emminent ſeates, my Lords the Preſidents, hauing their Morters of gold on their heads, and in their ſcarlet Robes lyned with Ermines, and the Councellors of the Court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the like Gownes.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide fate alone the Prouoſt of the Marchants, in a long Robe of Crimſon and violet veluet, being accompanyed with the Shirifes of the Towne.</p>
            <p>In the Quyer of the ſaid Church, was there more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer another floore raiſed three ſteps high, vpon which was another great Canopie, where the King, the Queenes, and Monſieur the Kings Brother were pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and conducted by the fore-named Duke of
<pb facs="tcp:8183:5"/> 
               <hi>Chevreuſe</hi> &amp; the Ambaſſadours, who withdrew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues into the Archbiſhops Pallace vntill the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice was ended, and then afterwards returned to the King and the Queenes.</p>
            <p>Prayers being done, they returned all in the like order as before into the Archbiſhops Pallace, where the whole Court ſupped.</p>
            <p>During which, was heard ſuch a noyſe and thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring of Cannon, as men would haue iudged that heauen and earth had ioyned together: In the like ſort Bon-fires, ſquibes, and ſuch like were not ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red throughout all the ſtreetes: and it may well be verified that France neuer ſawe ſo much reioycing.</p>
            <p>And God I pray, who hath euer beene propitious vnto vs, maintaine our Countrie in her greatneſſe, and graunt our King a glorious triumphe ouer his enemies, and a large extent of his Dominions.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="order">
            <pb facs="tcp:8183:5"/>
            <head>The Order of the Royall Feaſt.</head>
            <p>THe Suppper was kept in the Archbiſhops great Hall, and the Table reached from the one end thereof vnto the other,</p>
            <p>The King ſate in the middeſt of the Table, ſerued by my Lord the great Prior, who repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented the great Maſters perſon, before him there marched a number of Drummes, Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets and Clairons, accompanyed with Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>de Beaumont,</hi> great Steward of the Kings Houſe, and thirtie two others Stewards of his Maieſties Houſe-hold, with their ſtaues in their hands.</p>
            <p>The meate was carryed by my Lords the Princes, Dukes, Peeres, and Marſhals of France, followed by the Gentlemen of the Court and their ſeruants.</p>
            <p>Monſieur de <hi>Joinuille</hi> ſerued as great Pant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, Monſieur <hi>d' Elboeuf</hi> as Cup-bearer, and my Lord the Earle of <hi>Harcourt</hi> as Caruer.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8183:6"/>
            <p>The Queene Mother ſate on the right hand of the King, ſerued by my Lords the Dukes of <hi>Belgarde, d'Vzais,</hi> and <hi>Luxembourg.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Queene her ſelfe on the right hand of the Queene Mother, ſerued by my Lords the Dukes <hi>d' Alvin, Briſſac,</hi> and de <hi>Chaune.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Queene of great Brittaine ſate on the Kings left hand, ſerued by the Marſhall de <hi>Vitry</hi> as great Pantler, the Marſhall <hi>d' Aubeterre</hi> as Cup bearer, and my Lord of <hi>Baſſompierre</hi> as Caruer.</p>
            <p>My Lord the Duke of <hi>Chevrouſe</hi> ſate next the Queene of great Brittaine, ſerued by the Lord of <hi>Rochefort.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The extraordinarie Ambaſſadous of great Brittaine ſate next vnto the afore ſaid Duke of <hi>Chevreuſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Lord the Kings Brother ſate neere vnto the Queene, and next them all the Princes, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in moſt magnificent and Royall manner.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb facs="tcp:8183:6"/>
            <head>The Kings Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, contayning a Prohibition vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all his Subiects, to haue any Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique or Commerce with the Kingdome of <hi>Spaine,</hi> Publiſhed in the Parliament the 12. of <hi>May.</hi>
            </head>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="declaration">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>EVVIS by the grace</hi> of God King of <hi>France</hi> and of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> To all vnto whom theſe pre-ſent Letters ſhall come greeting. Vpon the complaints which haue bin made vnto vs by many of our Subiectes traffiquing into <hi>Spaine,</hi> of a Decree made the <hi>2.</hi> of this month by our moſt deare &amp; wellbe-loued Brother, and Brother in law, the Catholique King, vnto his Officers, to ſeaze vpon and ſtay in all his Ports and Hauens, the Shippes, Goods, and Merchandize of the French (our Subiects:) vnder pretext of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſals of ſome ſummes of money, which Our moſt deare and well-beloued Couſin, the Duke
<pb facs="tcp:8183:7"/> of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> our Gouernour and Lieuetenant Generall in <hi>Prouence,</hi> did make ſtay of certaine Barques, not far from <hi>Marſeilles,</hi> as belonging vnto ſome <hi>Genoway</hi> Mercha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts: as alſo becauſe they haunted the deſert Hauens of our ſaid Country of <hi>Prouence,</hi> to the preiudice of our Ordinances &amp; Prouiſions made by Our Court of Parliament of <hi>Aix:</hi> The ſaid King prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding that ſome part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid mony did appertain vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Subiects (which is a thing not yet ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified) and part thereof vnto the ſaid <hi>Genowaies.</hi> NOW therefore, becauſe it is a matter of great importance for our Subiects good, to preuent them from receauing any further loſſe or hinderance of ſuch their ſeizure and detenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their Shippes and Goods as is ordained in <hi>Spaine,</hi> wherein there can be no better or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der taken, then a generall interdiction of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce in thoſe places, where the Merchants Our Subiects can no longer be at their liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. WEE make it knowne, That hauing deliberated of this affayre in Our Councell, where was preſent Our moſt honoured Lady and Mother, ſome Princes of Our Blood, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Princes and Officers of Our Crowne, Lords and notable Perſonages of Our ſayed Councell, <hi>WITH THEIR ADVICE,</hi> and of Our owne knowledge, full power and royall Authority, We haue made, and doe by theſe preſents, ſigned with Our hand, make
<pb facs="tcp:8183:7"/> moſt expreſſe prohibition vnto all Our Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, of what Quality and Condition ſoeuer they be, to haue any Trafique or Commerce in the Kingdome of <hi>Spaine,</hi> of any Corne, Wine, Cordage, and generaly neither to carry thither, tranſport or buy any Merchandize whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, vpon paine vnto the Offenders, of the confiſcation of their Veſſels and Goods, and to bee puniſhed according to the rigour of Our Lawes: and this to continue vntill a reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be fully made of Our Subiects Goods ſeazed vpon in <hi>Spaine,</hi> or that by Our Letters Pattents We ſhall otherwiſe ordaine.</p>
                  <p>WHEREFORE Wee charge and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand all Our louing and loyall Officers in Our Courts of Parliament, that they cauſe theſe Our preſent Letters to be read, publiſhed and Regiſtred, and the contents thereof to bee kept and executed each one apart, and Our ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Procurors or their Subſtitutes, to make for the due execution of the ſame, all diligent &amp; neceſſary perſuite and inquirie.</p>
                  <p>Alſo We giue charge vnto Our Gouernors, and Our Liuetenants Generall in Our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces, particuler Captaines and Gouernors of Our Towns and places, chiefely thoſe vpon Our Frontiers, and the Bayliffes, Seneſhals, and Prouoſts of Our moſt deare Couſins, the Conſtable &amp; Marſhals of <hi>France,</hi> or their Lieue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenants, And vnto all Our Iuſtices, Officers,
<pb facs="tcp:8183:8"/> and Subiects, to aſſiſt vnto the due execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe preſents: for ſuch is Our pleaſure.</p>
                  <p>In Witneſſe whereof, Wee haue cauſed Our Seale to be put vnto theſe aforeſaid preſents.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Giuen at <hi>Paris</hi>
                        </hi> 
                        <date>
                           <hi>the 23. of <hi>Aprill;</hi> in the yeare of Grace, 1625. and of Our Raigne the fifteenth.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Lewis. And vppon the Fowld By the King. De Lomenie.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>And Sealed with the Great Seale of yellow Waxe, vpon double taile: And vpon the Fowld hereof is written:</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="postscript">
               <body>
                  <p>Read, publiſhed, and regiſtred in Court, yea and the Kings Atturney generall requiring the ſame to be put in execution, kept, and obſerued according to their tennor and forme, and collected Copies of the ſame to be ſent to the Bayliffes and Seneſhals of that Iuriſdiction, to be there likewiſe read, publiſhed, and executed by the diligence of the Subſtitutes of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forſaid generall Atturney, which he enioyneth to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the Court hereof within the month. In the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamement at <hi>Paris</hi> the 12. of <hi>May,</hi> 1625.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Signed Du Tillet. Cum Priuiligio Maieſtatie</signed>
                     <dateline>Imprinted at <hi>Paris,</hi> 
                        <date>1625.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="fre" type="description">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:8183:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Le Triomphe glorieux &amp; l'ordre des Ceremonies obſeruees au mariage du Roy de la Grand' Bretagne, &amp; de Madame ſoeur du Roy. <hi>Enſemble l'ordre tenu aux fiançailles faictes au Chaſteau du Louure, en la Chambre de ſa Majeſté.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>EN fin le ciel propice a la France, a voulu ce qu'elle re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire, il y a ſi long temps. Les nuages qui ſembloient vouloir obſcurcir ſon eſclat, &amp; qui auoient comme con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire de faire mourir le fruict en ſa fleur, ſont maintenant diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipez, &amp; cette mauuaiſe influence eſt aneantie a ce coup, Dicu a permis par vne volonte ſecrete, que les deux plus puiſſantes Couronnes de la Chreſtiente ſoient vnies enſemble, par le plus celebre mariage qui ſe ſoit iamais veu dedans l'Vniuers. C'eſt donc auiourd'huy que tant de felicite, de gloire, &amp; de bon-heur ne promettent pas moins a noſtre grand Roy, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincible LOVYS LE IVSTE, que l'Empire de tout le mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. Quel contentement a la France, &amp; quel profit a la grand' Bretagne, de ſe voir vnies ſi inſeparablement, par vn noeud plus indiſſoluble que le gordien, &amp; par vne amitie mieux ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentee que les murs Babiloniens fondez par Semiramis? Il n'y a point d'ennemis aſſez forts pour esbranler iamais deux Royaumes ſi floriſſans, qui puiſent leur grandeur du ciel, &amp; borner leur puiſſance de toute la terre. Reſiouiſſons nous donc, bons François, a ceſte heure que les aduerſaires de l'E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtat tremblant de peur &amp; de crainte, ont leur ame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>migeed v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne il belle alliance. Mais pour en laiſſer la memoire eternel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, &amp; la donner eſt depoſt a la poſterite. Ie veux deſcrire icy
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:8183:9"/> le plus ſuccintement qu'il me ſera poſſible, les magnificences, les triomphes, &amp; l'ordre veritable de cet heureux mariage.</p>
            <p>Le Ieudy huictieſme iour de May, le Roy paroiſſant de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dans ſa chambre comme vn beau Soleil qui luit au deſſus de tous les autres Aſtres, ayant auec luy la Royne ſeconde lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miere, Monſieur ſon frere vnique, Meſſieurs les Ducs de Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours &amp; d'Elboeuf, Mareſchaux de Vitry &amp; de Baſſom-pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, &amp; autres Seigneurs de la Cour, enuoya querir Madame, qui y fut aſſiſtee par la Royne ſa mere, Meſdames les Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes de Conde &amp; de Conty, Meſdames les Ducheſſes de Guyſe, de Cheureuſe, &amp; d'Elboeuf, &amp; pluſieurs autres gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des Dames. Sa robe eſtoit de toile d'or &amp; d'argent toute par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemee de fleurs de Lys d'or, &amp; enrichie de pluſieurs diamants, &amp; autres pierres precieuſes. La queue de ladite robe eſtoit portee par Madamoiſelle de Bourbon.</p>
            <p>Comme elle fut entree dedans la chambre du Roy auec v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Maieſte digne de ſa naiſſance, Meſſieurs les Comtes de Carlile, &amp; Milor Holand, Ambaſſadeurs pour le Roy de la Grand' Bretagne, y entrerent auſſi toſt, veſtus auec le plus bel aduantage qui ſe puiſſe dire, donnant au Roy le contract de mariage, qui fut leu tout haut par Monſeigneur le Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celier, apres que ſa Maieſte eut agree les conuenances. Les Ambaſſadeurs ſe retirerent en la chambre de Monſeigneur le Duc de Cheureuſe, au deſſus de celle du Roy, &amp; luy ayant fait entendre les accords. Il fut trouuer auſſi toſt ſa Maieſtie, accompagne deſdits ſieurs Ambaſſadeurs &amp; pluſieurs autres Seigneurs de marque, eſtant veſtu d'vn habit noir a bandes toutes garnies de diamants, &amp; les fer d'aiguillettes en eſtoient enrichis.</p>
            <p>Arriue deuant ſa Maieſte il luy preſenta ſa procuration &amp; le pouuoir que luy auoit donne le Roy de la Grand' Bretagne, qui <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut inc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ce au bout dudit contract de mariage, que le Roy ſig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a, Madame, les Roynes, Monſeigneur le Duc de Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ureuſe, &amp; Meſſieurs les Ambaſſadeurs. Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a fait &amp; arreſte,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:8183:9"/> Monſieur le Cardinal de la Roche-foucaut fit les fiançailles a la maniere accouſtumee.</p>
            <p>Comme vne telle vnion ne ſe pouuoit pas paracheuer ſans de grandes pompes, &amp; d'infinies reſiouiſſances.</p>
            <p>L'Egliſe de Noſtre-Dame fut choiſie pour les ceremonies de l'accompliſſement du mariage, &amp; fut toute tendue de ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches tapiſſeries, tiſſues de ſoye, d'or &amp; d'argent.</p>
            <p>L'on eſleua enuiron de huict pieds de terre, vne belle &amp; longue gallerie, qui prenoit ſon commencement des l'entree de la maiſon Archi-Epiſcopale, &amp; ſe venoit rendre a l'entree du Coeur de ladite Egliſe. Elle eſtoit ſouſtenue de pluſieurs pilliers, couuerte par le haut de ſatin violet, tout brode de fleur de Lys d'or, &amp; par le bas d'vne belle toile de lin ciree, par deſſus laquelle paſſerent toutes les ceremonies du mariage, comme il s'enſuit.</p>
            <p>Premierement, les cent Suiſſes des Gardes du corps du Roy, veſtus des liurees de ſa Maieſte, le tambour battant, &amp; l'enſeigne deſployee.</p>
            <p>Douze haut-bois veſtus de ſemblables liurees qui rauiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoient par leurs ſons agreables les ames par les oreilles.</p>
            <p>Huict tambours couuerts de pareilles parures battoient ſi furieuſement que les courages les moins hardis s'animoient au bruit d'vn tel tintamarre.</p>
            <p>Dix trompettes faiſoient ſauter de ioye &amp; d'alegreſſe les coeurs dedans les corps.</p>
            <p>Monſieur de Rodes Grand Maiſtre des Ceremonies mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choit apres tout cela, veſtu a l'aduantage &amp; fort bien ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compagne.</p>
            <p>Apres luy Meſſieurs les Cheualiers de l'Ordre du S. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſprit tous brillans de pierreries.</p>
            <p>Sept Herauts d'armes alloient en ſuitte auec leur cottes de velours rouge cramoiſy fleurdeliſees d'or.</p>
            <p>Meſſieurs de Vitry &amp; de Baſſompierre, Mareſchaux de France.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:8183:10"/>
            <p>Monſieur le Duc d'Elboeuf.</p>
            <p>Monſeigneur le Duc de Cheureuſe, veſtu d'vn habit de d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ap noir tout couppe &amp; d'ouble de toile d'or auec vne toc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que auſſi de velours noir, ſur ſa teſte vne enſeigne qui esblo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyſſoit la veue par ſon eſclat, vne eſcrape toute couuerte de roſes de diamants, vn capot tout brode d'or &amp; ſeme de pierreries.</p>
            <p>Meſſieurs les deux Ambaſſadeurs Extraordinaires, tous deux couuerts de toile d'argent batu auec la toque.</p>
            <p>Le Roy auec vn habit tout en broderie d'or &amp; d'argent, tenant a ſa main droite Madame, qui auoit vne Couronne ſur la teſte, &amp; ſa robe toute parſemee de fleurs de Lys d'or.</p>
            <p>Monſieur de l'autre coſte qui la tenoit de ſa main gauche auſſi ſuperbement veſtu.</p>
            <p>La Royne mere.</p>
            <p>La Royne couuerte d'vne robe toute brodee d'or, d'argent &amp; de pierreries.</p>
            <p>Meſdames les Princeſſes de Conde &amp; de Conty, portans la longue queue de ladite robe.</p>
            <p>Madamoiſelle de Mont-penfier.</p>
            <p>Madame la Comteſſe de Soiſſons.</p>
            <p>Madame de Guyſe.</p>
            <p>Madame de Cheureuſe.</p>
            <p>Madame d'Elboeuf.</p>
            <p>Et tous les autres Seigneurs &amp; Dames de la Cour queie ne peux ſpecifier par le menu, tant le nombre eſtoit grand.</p>
            <p>Toute ceſte Royale &amp; genereuſe troupe s'arreſta a l'entree du grand portail de ladite Egliſe au deuant duquel eſtoit vn grand parterre deſtine pour faire le mariage, &amp; ou eſtoit eſleue au deſſus vn grand poeſle d'vne valeur ineſtimable, ſous le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quel le Roy &amp; Monſieur ſon frere quitta Madame, la mirent entre les mains de Monſeigneur le Duc de Cheureuſe, &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors Monſieur le Cardinal de la Roche-foucault eſpouſa Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dame, auec les ceremonies ordinaires de l'Egliſe.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:8183:10"/>
            <p>Dela tout l'ordre cy-deſſus s'en alla dedans le coeur par vne longue gallerie qui eſt oit allignee au milieu de la Nef de l'Egliſe toute couuerte de tapiſſerie, la plus bell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> qui ſe peuſt iamais voir.</p>
            <p>Au milieu dudit coeur eſtoient deſ-ja placez d'vn coſte en des ſieges eminents, Meſſeigneurs les Preſidents ayant leur mortier d'or ſur la teſte veſtus de leur robes d'eſcatlates dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blees d'hermines, &amp; Meſſieurs les Conſeillers auecques de ſemblables robes.</p>
            <p>De l'autre coſte proiſſoit a part Monſieur le Prouoſt des Marchands, conuert d'vne longue robe de velours rouge cramoiſcy &amp; violet, aſſiſte des Eſcheuins du corps de ville.</p>
            <p>Dans le coeur de ladite Egliſe eſtoit eſleue de trois mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches vn par-terre, au deſſus duquel eſtoit vn autre grand po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſle, ou le Roy, les Roynes, &amp; Monſieur furent placez, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duits par leſdits Duc de Cheurcuſe &amp; Ambaſſadeurs, leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quels ſe retirenta l'Archeueſche iuſqu'a ce que le ſeruice fut acheue, puis y retournerent trouuer le Roy &amp; les Roynes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pres la fin de l'office.</p>
            <p>Leurs oraiſons finies, ils s'en retournerent au meſme ordre dedans l'Archeueſche, ou toute la Cour ſoupa.</p>
            <p>Et puis en meſme temps, l'on ouyt vn tel bruit des coups de canons qui ſe tirerent, que l'on euſt dit que la terre &amp; le ciel ſe vouloient ioindre enſemble.</p>
            <p>Les feus de ioye &amp; d'artifices ſe firent par toutes les reus, &amp; l'on peut dire auec verite, que iamais la France n'cuſt plus de reſiouyſſances.</p>
            <p>Dieu qui luy a eſte touſiours fauourable la maintienne en ſa grandeur, &amp; face que ſon grand Roy triomphe glorieux de tous ſes ennemis, &amp; borne ſes terres de l'enclos de tout le monde.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="fre" type="order">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:8183:11"/>
            <head>L'ordre du festin Royal.</head>
            <p>LE ſoupper fut dans la grand' Salle lambriſſee de l'Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheueſche, &amp; la table tenoit d'vn bout a l'autre.</p>
            <p>Le Roy eſtoit au milieu de la table, ſeruy par Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur le Grand Prieur, repreſentant Monſieur le Grand Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre, deuant luy marchoient nombre de tambours, trompet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes &amp; clairons, accompagne de Monſieur de Beaumont pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mier Maiſtre d'Hoſtel, &amp; trente-deux Maiſtres d'Hoſtel, tous le baſton a la main.</p>
            <p>La viande eſtoit portee apres eux par Noſſeigneurs les Princes, Ducs, Pairs, &amp; Mareſchaux de France, ſuiuis des Gentils hommes de Cour &amp; ſeruans, Monſieur de Ioinuille ſeruoit de grand Panetier: Monſieur d'Elbeuf d'<hi>Eſchanſon,</hi> &amp; Monſieur le Comte d'Arcourt d'Eſeuyer tranchant.</p>
            <p>La Royne Mere au coſte droict du Roy, ſeruie par Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieurs le Ducs de Bellegarde, d'Vzais &amp; Luxebourg.</p>
            <p>La Royne ſur le coſte droict de la Royne Mere ſeruie par Meſſieurs le Ducs d'Aluin, Briſſac, &amp; de Chaune.</p>
            <p>La Royne d'Angleterre a coſte gauche du Roy, ſeruie par Meſſieurs les Mareſchaux de Vitry, comme grand Panetier: Monſieur le Mareſchal d'Auloterre Eſchanſon; &amp; Monſieur de Baſſompierre Eſcuyer trenchant.</p>
            <p>Monſieur le Duc de Cheureuſe ſous la Reyne d'Angli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terre ſeruy par le Sieur de R.</p>
            <p>Les Ambaſſadeurs extraordinaires d'Angliterre pres du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit Sieur de Cheureuſe.</p>
            <p>Monſigneur frere de ſa Majeſte eſtoit aſſis aupres de la Royne, &amp; toutes les Princeſſes a la table, qui fut ſeruy auec quantite de ſeruices autant magnifiques que ſplendides &amp; Royaux.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="fre" type="declaration">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:8183:11"/>
            <head>Declaration du Roy, portant defenſes à tous ſes ſubjets de faire aucun traficq ny commerce au Royaume d'Eſpagne. <hi>Publiée en Parliment le douzieſme, May,</hi> 1625.</head>
            <p>LOVIS par la grace de Dieu, Roy de France &amp; de Nauarre, A tous ceux qui ces preſentes Lettres ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ront, Salut. Sur les plaintes qui nous ont eſte faictes de la part de pluſieurs de nos ſubjets traffiquans en Eſpagne, d'vne Ordonnance decernee le deuxieſme de ce mois, par noſtre tres-cher &amp; tres-ame bon frere &amp; beaufrere le Roy Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique, a ſes officiers, pour ſaiſir &amp; arreſter en ſes ports &amp; haures les nauires, effects &amp; marchandiſes des François nos ſubjets, ſous pretexte de repreſailles de quelque ſomme d'ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent que noſtre tres-cher &amp; bien-ame Coufin le Duc de Guyſe, Gouerneur &amp; noſtre Lieutenant general en Prouince, afaict arreſter dans des barques es enuirons de noſtre ville de Marſeille, comme appertenans a des marchands Geneuois, auſſi qu'ils alloient dans les ports des-habitez de noſtredit pais de Prouence, au preiudice de nos Ordonnances, &amp; des Arreſts de noſtre Cour de Parlement d'Aix: Pretendant le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit Roy, que partie dudit argent appartient a ſes ſubjets (choſe qui n'a point eſte verifice) en partie aux Geneuois. Et d'autant qu'il importe pour le bien de nos ſubjets, d'em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſcher qu'ils ne puiſſent receuoir plus grande perte &amp; dom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage de la ſaiſie &amp; detention de leurs nauires &amp; biens, qui eſt ordonnee en Eſpagne: a quoy il ne peut eſtre plus conuena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blement pourueu, que par vne interdiction generale du com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce au lieu ou les marchands nos ſubjets ne ſont plus en liberte: SCAVOIR faiſons, Qu'ayant mis cet affaire en de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation en noſtre Conſeil, ou eſtoient la Royne noſtre tres-honoree Dame &amp; Mere, aucuns Princes de noſtre Sang, autres Princes &amp; Officiers de noſtre Couronne, Seigneurs &amp; notables perſonnages de noſtredit Conſeil: DE L'ADVIS d'iceluy, &amp; de noſtre certaine ſcience, pleine puiſſance &amp; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorite
<pb facs="tcp:8183:12"/> Royale, Nous auons faict &amp; faiſons par ce preſentes ſignees de noſtre main, tres-expreſſes inhibitions &amp; defenſes a tous nos ſubjets de quelque qualite &amp; condition qu'ils ſoient, de faire aucun trafficq ny commerce au Royaume d'<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Eſpagne, de Bleds, Vins, toyles, cordages: &amp; generalement d'y mener, conduire, tranſporter ny achepter aucunes mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſes de quelque qualite que ce ſoit, ſur peine aux con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treuenans de confiſcation de leurs marchandiſes, vaiſſeaux &amp; effects, &amp; d'eſtre punis &amp; chaſtiez ſelon la rigueur de nos Ordonnances, &amp; ſe iuſques a ce quela main leuee des effects ſaiſis en Eſpagne ſur nos ſubjets, aye eſte pleinement donnee, &amp; que par nos Lettres patentes Nous en ayons autrement ordonne. SI DONNONS en mandement a nos amez &amp; feaux les gens tenans nos Cours de Parlements, Que ces preſentes ils facent lire, publier &amp; enregiſtrer, &amp; le contenu en icelles, garder &amp; executer exactement chacun endroit ſoy, &amp; a nos Procureurs generaux ou leurs Subſtituts, de faire pour l'execution d'icelles, toutes pourſuites &amp; diligences re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſes &amp; neceſſaires. Mandons auſſi aux Gouuerneurs &amp; nos Lieutenans generaux en nos Prouinces, Capitaines &amp; Gou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerneurs particuliers de nos Villes &amp; places, meſmes celles qui ſont ſur nos frontiers, Baillifs, Seneſchaux, Preuoſts de nos tres-chers Couſins le Coneſtable &amp; Mareſchaux de France ou leurs Lieutenans, &amp; a tous autres nos Iuſticiers &amp; Officiers &amp; ſubiets, de tenir la main a l'execution de ces pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentes: CAR tel eſt noſtre plaiſir. En teſmoin de quoy, Nous auons faict mettre noſtre ſeel a ceſdites preſentes.</p>
            <p>Do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne a Paris le vingt troiſieſme iour d'Auril, l'an de grace mil ſix cens vingt-cinq. Et de noſtre regne le quinzieſme, Signe, <hi>LOVIS.</hi> Et ſur le reply, Par le Roy, DE LOMENIE.</p>
            <p>Et ſcellees du grand ſceau de cire iaune ſur double queue. Et ſur ledit reply eſt cſcrit,
<floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="fre">
                  <body>
                     <p>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ues, publices &amp; regiſtres és Regiſtres d'icelle: Ouy, &amp; ce requerant le Procureur General du Roy, pour eſtre executees, gardees &amp; obſeruees ſelon leur forme &amp; te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neur, &amp; copies collationnees d'icelles enuoyees aux Bailliages &amp; Seneſchauſſees de ce reſſort, pour yeſtre pareillement leues, publices, regiſtrees &amp; executees a la diligence des Subſtituts dudit Procureur General, auſquels enionct d'y tenir la main, &amp; d'en certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fier la Cour auoir ce faict au mois. A Paris en Parlement le douzieſme iour de May mil ſix cens vingt-cinq.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Sifine, DV TILLET.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8183:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
